Guide to the Alumni Class materials, 1823-1998 MS2130
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Scrapbooks, 1925-1933; MS2130 Series 3; 3..5 Linear Feet Two oversize boxes (Box 36, Box 9, Box 16, Box 25, Box 8, Flat box 33)
  - Francis Strayer football scrapbook, 1927 -1993 -- --ca. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    This scrapbook contains clippings from Francis Henry Strayer's football career. They include newspaper articles, football programs, and certificates. They range in date from 1927 to ca 1993.
    Francis Strayer presented these materials to the university in October of 1993. Strayer was a 1934 graduate of the university, playing both football and baseball for GW.
    This note was written in 2005. Formerly Acc 203.
  - Hattie Strong scrapbook, 1937 -1938 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    This scrapbook was created by George Washington University (GWU) Trustee, Hattie Strong. It consists of letters, news clippings, and photographs. Moreover, this scrapbook includes information concerning Strong's election into the Board of Trustees, as well as the dedication of Strong Hall. Also included is correspondence between Strong and GWU President Marvin. These items range in date from 1937-1938.
    Ms. Hattie Strong was a member of the GW Board of Trustees and a benefactor to the University. Hattie Maria Corrin was born in South Coventry, Connecticut on October 23, 1864. In 1905 she married Henry Alvah Strong, co-founder and first president of Eastman Kodak Company. Henry Strong died in 1919. In 1928 Ms. Strong created the Hattie Strong Foundation dedicated to helping students and enriching non-profit colleges. In 1937 Strong Hall (at 620 21st Street) was dedicated on the GW campus. The residence hall for women was the result of a $200,000 dollar gift from Hattie Strong. Ms. Strong died on June 6, 1950 in Winston-Salem, North Carolina.
    This note was written in 2005.
    Formerly ACC#249.
  - Gertrude Metcalf Scrapbook, 09/21/1891 --06/01/1898 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Materials in this collection include one 145-page scrapbook of new clippings, report cards, exam questions, photographs, and invitations. They range in date from 1891-98.
    Some of the professors represented are: Wilbur, Munroe (a number of articles), Hodgkins, Swisher, Huntington, Montague, Lodge, Pollard, Farquhar, Gore, George Smith, Sterrett, Shoenfield, and Mason.
    There are also clippings on Columbian Women. For the class of 1897: Grace Ross, Agnes Claney, Helen Biddis, Anna Kelton, L.B. Holbrook, Ruth McGowan. For the class of 1899: Katherine Yancy, Etheldreda Norris, Lida Draper, Alice McKelden, Frances Newlands.
    Also, on page 93 there is an article about the location of the University remaining in the District. This was during the time when the "Welling Plan" proposed moving the University to the Mall.
    The scrapbook was donated to the Lisner Library (and subsequently transferred to University Archives) by Mrs. Milmae Gray, March 16, 1960.
    Gertrude Elizabeth Metcalf graduated from Columbian University in 1898. This scrapbook is self-titled "Glimpses of School Days in Print and Pictures by G.E.M. [her initials] Central High School, Sept 21, 1891-June 24, 1894 Columbian University Sept. 24, 1894-June 1, 18[98]". This scrapbook is a wonderful reflection of university life during 1894-1898. The first part covers her days at Central High School in Washington (including report cards) and schedules of classes taken.
    The second part covers Metcalf's student days at GW (then Columbian University) broken down by year, and includes invitations, photos, news clippings and report cards. It also includes examination questions for scholarships in French, German, and English that she might have taken. Some of the professors she has clippings of include Wilbur, Munroe (a number of articles), Hodgkins, Swisher, Huntington, Montague, Lodge, Pollard, Farquhar, Gore, George Smith, Sterrett, Shoenfield, and Mason.
    There are also clipping on Columbian Women. For the class of 1897: Grace Ross, Agnes Claney, Helen Biddis, Anna Kelton, L.B. Holbrook, Ruth McGowan. For the class of 1899: Katherine Yancy, Etheldreda Norris, Lida Draper, Alice McKelden, Frances Newlands.
    Also, on page 93 there is an article about the location of the University remaining in the district. This was during the time when the "Welling Plan" proposed moving the university to the Mall.
    Formerly Acc 951.
    N.B. This scrapbook is very fragile and should not be photocopied.
  - World War II scrapbook and magazines, 1941 -1945 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Ruth Ann Parker Wells graduated with an A.B. degree in Home Economics from George Washington University in 1934. This collection includes two letters (ca.1944), a gas ration book and sticker, three Office of Price Administration "blue points," three "Time" magazines, and a scrapbook of World War II clippings (including many cartoons by Jim Berryman and articles on Civil Defense). Formerly ACC#463.
  - Scrapbook of Garnett Jex relating to the mural "The Planning of Washington", 1930 -1931 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Scrapbook of correspondence, newspaper articles, photographs, sketches of Garnett Jex relating to his 1931 M.S. thesis at The George Washington University and the mural "The Planning of Washington," which depicts George Washington laying out the National Capital. (See also RG0031/001). Garnet Jex earned both his B.A.(1927) and M.A. (1931) from The George Washington University. He was born in Kent, Ohio in 1895. He died in 1979 after a long career as a landscape painter, portraitist and illustrator. After World War I, he spent the remainder of his life in Washington, D.C. While working on his master degree from GW he worked as a medical illustrator for the Army Medical Corps. Formerly ACC#852.
  - Scrapbook of James Jenks, 1895 -1897 (Flat box 33, Folder 1)
    Scrapbook of James Edward Jenks, who earned an LL.B. from Columbian University in 1897. Includes clippings, cards, and programs: Lafayette Square Opera House, Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad route, postcard of Cabin John bridge, Columbian University Law School (1896 exam questions, 1897 commencement invitation, Phi Delta Phi), Grand Opera House, National Theater, Academy of Music, U.S. Congress gallery passes, First Congregational Church (10th and G Streets, N.W.), Calvary Baptist Church (8th and H, Streets N.W.), First Presbyterian Church, Presidential Inaugural Concerts (1897), assassination of Lincoln, William McKinley elected President, Catholic University, American University, Justice Stephen J. Field. Gift of Judson A. Grenier, 2005.
  - Ledger of GW Glee Club, 1930-1932 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    GWU Glee Club Record book complied by Samuel Detwiler. Contains calendars, officers, attendance, enrollment (with names, addresses, voice, etc.), minutes, engagements, songs sung, press notices, and two photos. Also included is separate booklet with names, notes on events, and attendance. The materials date from 1930-1932.
  - Scrapbook of Joan MacFarland Loar, 1925-1930; Series 3 (Box 40, Scrapbook 1)
    Scrapbook belonging to alumna Jean MacFarland Loar, AB and B Dip in Education with distinction, 1929. Includes clippings, - some of which are annotated - correspondence, programs and play bills, dance cards, tickets, business and calling cards, intivations, greeting cards, and postcards pertaining to life at The George Washington University and the Mid-Atlantic region.
    Joan M. Loar was born August 1, 1908 in Vale Summit, Allegany, Maryland to John Herbert Loar and Mary Ann Greenhorn. She attended Potomac State School in Keyser, West Virginia. Ms. Loar graduated from The George Washinto University in 1929. She was married to Lester Reynolds on January 17, 1934 in Baltimore, Maryland. Ms. Loar died February 3, 2000.
  - Scrapbooks of Susan Schein, 1963-1965 (Box 42)
    Two scrapbooks documenting the time of Susan Schein (GW class of 1966) at GW. The scrapbooks contain primarily mementos from social events and newspaper clippings about GW. Schein was active in her sorority and was friends with Lynda Johnson, both of which are reflected in her scrapbooks. Also included is a program from "An American Pageant of the Arts," the 1962 event hosted by Mrs. Kennedy and Mrs. Eisenhower to fund raise for what would become the Kennedy Center, and the 1963-64 GW student handbook.
  - Scrapbooks of Susan Schein, 1963-1965 (Box 43)
- Personal papers, 1823-1993; MS2130 Series 4; 4 Linear feet (Box 27, Box 30, Box 12, Box 32, Box 3, Box 39, Flat box 24, Box 34, Box 15)
  This collection includes an autograph book, diary, letter, diploma, journal, newclippings, and ephemera. They range in date from 1823 to 1993.
  - Autograph book, 1861-1862 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Autograph book of Thomas Edwin Brown (1841-1924), an alumnus of Columbian College, now George Washington University. Contains autographs of classmates at Columbian College, some professors, and his parents. Autographs include: G.W. Samson and Elliott Coues. Bound in black leather over boards; cover stamped in gold and stamped and framed in blind, a.e.g. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 68.
  - Jonathan Tilson Diary, 1842-1848, 1842 -1859 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Diary of Jonathan Tilson (1818-1908). Baptist minister in Hingham, Mass. and Rowley, Mass. and graduate of Columbian College, later George Washington University (B.A. 1848, A.M., 1851) and headmaster, 1848-1849, of the Columbian Preparatory School. Half the diary, 1842-1844, and 1851-1859, covers teaching and religious work in the Boston area. The rest, 1844-1850, covers student life at Columbian College, Washington, D.C., during the administration of Joel Smith Bacon. Mentioned also are A.J. Huntington, professor of Greek and Latin, and former president Stephen Chapin. Other topics include the Smithsonian Institution, Georgetown University, and the inauguration of President James K. Polk. Purchase, 1982. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 2.
  - Letter of thanks from Louis P. Harrison, 08/12/1993 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Letter of thanks from Louis P. Harrison to George Washington University for the education he recieved. He says he received a bachelor's degree in physics, and then worked for the Federal government, retiring as a physisist fo the U.S. Weather Service in 1969. Formerly ACC#1020.
  - Helen Lily Voerge, papers, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Helen Lily Voerge graduated with a B.A. from the Columbian College of George Washington University in 1948. This collection includes her diploma and commencement program; a pamphlet titled "Collected Papers of Herbert Barton Brooks"; and unidentified photo. Donaton from Sue Austin in 2001. Formerly ACC#967.
  - Journal of Thomas Dawes Eliot, 1823 -1824 (Flat box 24)
    Thomas Dawes Eliot (1808-70) was born in Boston, Massachusetts, March 20, 1808, and died in New Bedford, Massachusetts, June 12, 1870. He earned an A.B. in 1825 and an A.M. in 1829 from Columbian College (the first name of what became The George Washington University in 1904). He studied law in Washington and New Bedford, and was admitted to the Massachusetts bar.
    After being a member of both houses of the legislature, he was elected to Congress as a Whig, to fill the unexpired term of Zeno Scudder, serving from April 17, 1854 to March 3, 1855, and making an eloquent speech on the Kansas Nebraska bill, which was published (Washington, 1854). He was prominent in the Free-soil convention at Worcester, Massachusetts, in 1855, and on the dissolution of the Whig party was active among the founders of the Republican Party in Massachusetts. He declined its nomination for attorney general in 1857, but was afterward elected to Congress again for five successive terms, serving from 1859-69. Mr. Eliot took an active part in the proceedings of the house, particularly in the legislation on the protection and well-being of African-Americans.
    Materials in this collection include a journal Elliot kept while a student at Columbian College and includes notes on lectures given by college President William Staughton, and Elliot's own orations. It ranges in date from 1823-24. The provenance of this journal is unknown, it was discovered in a box of back log material and accessioned in Aug. 2001. Formerly ACC#1010.
  - Program and news clippings, 1909 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include a program from the Calcium Clubs and news clippings on the club and GW President Needham. They date from 1909. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Photos and news clippings, 1906 -1909 -- --ca. (Box 27, Folder 2)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include a photos and news clips. They date from 1906-ca.1909. Formerly ACC#869.
  - World War I news clippings, 1917 -1921 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include news clippings on World War I and Woodrow Wilson. They date from 1917-21. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Society page announcements, 1913 -1923 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include news clippings of society page announcements. They date from 1913-23. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Football team news clippings, 1908 -1909 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include news clippings of the football team and Calcium Club. They date from 1908-09. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Photo of James Moneyway and personal items, 1922 ca. (Box 27, Folder 6)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include a photo of Moneyway, U.S. Postal publications, and personal items. They date from ca.1922. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Fourth of July news clippings, 1913 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include news clippings of Fourth of July activities. They date from 1913. Formerly ACC#869.
  - GW Law School news clippings, 1912 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include news clippings of the GW Law School. They date from 1912. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Theater news clippings, 1917 -1924 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include news clippings on the theater. They date from 1917-24. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Programs, 1920 -1924 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include programs for the Democratic National Committee, Art Club Players, Choir of the First Baptist Church, Player's Club of Washington. They date from 1920-24. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Drama League Players of Washington, 1916 -1917 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include programs of the Drama League Players of Washington. They date from 1916-17. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Digest of Hooker's Ecclesiastical Polity, 1920 ca. (Box 27, Folder 12)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include "Digest of Hooker's Ecclesiastical Polity" by Moneyway, done as a student at GW with comment from William Allen Wilbur. It dates from c.1920. Formerly ACC#869.
  - A Discussion of Thakeray's Methods in Vanity Fair, 1920 ca. (Box 27, Folder 13)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include "A Discussion of Thakeray's Methods in Vanity Fair" by Moneyway. It dates from c.1920. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Postcards and song book, 1917 -1919 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include postcards sent to Moneyway from Europe and a booklet titled "Songs of the Soldiers and Sailors." They date from 1917-19. Formerly ACC#869.
  - The Lyric Poetry of Tennyson and other notes, 1920 ca. (Box 27, Folder 15)